<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain desires for the settlement and improving of ministers meanes. In two letters: the first, resolving how ministers meanes should be raised, whether by tythes, the peoples benevolencie, or a certain set stypeud [sic] from the publike. The second, shewing how ministers meanes might be leavied, and gathered without any trouble or charge to them, equally distributed to their and the peoples content, &amp; much improved without any wrong or injustice done to any. Published for the common good.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E357_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201143</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861693</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861693</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78469)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E357[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain desires for the settlement and improving of ministers meanes. In two letters: the first, resolving how ministers meanes should be raised, whether by tythes, the peoples benevolencie, or a certain set stypeud [sic] from the publike. The second, shewing how ministers meanes might be leavied, and gathered without any trouble or charge to them, equally distributed to their and the peoples content, &amp; much improved without any wrong or injustice done to any. Published for the common good.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G.E.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains only the first letter.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Salaries, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Salaries, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113834:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113834:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAIN DESIRES FOR The ſettlement and improving of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Meanes. <hi>IN TWO LETTERS:</hi> THE FIRST, Reſolving how Miniſters meanes ſhould be raiſed, whether by Tythes, the Peoples benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, or a certain ſet Stypend from the Publike. THE SECOND, Shewing how Miniſters meanes might be leavied, and gathered without any trouble or charge to them, equally diſtributed to their and the Peoples content, &amp; much improved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any wrong or injuſtice done to any.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed for the common good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>G. E.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113834:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113834:2"/>
            <head>THE FIRST LETTER, HOVV Miniſters meanes ſhould be raiſed; whether by Tithes, the Peoples benevolencie, or a certain ſet ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend from the Publike.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ACcording to your deſire, I ſent you my thoughts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the maintenance of Miniſters; a nice and an odious point in theſe times, and ſubject to many exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, and yet a neceſſary point to be diſcuſſed, for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of many Chriſtians, who are ſo diſtracted about it, partly by the tenderneſſe of their Conſciences, and partly by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Opinions, that they do not know which way to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace or to follow. I will tell you my mind plainly and fully, without any partiality, or by-reſpect, and the Lord direct you to chuſe the beſt way.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113834:3"/>
There are divers opinions now a dayes amongſt the Learned, and the ignorant about it, how and in what manner the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel ſhould be maintained in the Church of God. Not to ſpeak of thoſe, which would have Miniſters to ſerve frcely, and take no ſtipend at a l, but rather worke with their own hands, like other mechanicall Callings, and that as they ſay in imitation of the Apoſtle, Act. 20.34. 1 Cor. 4.12. Which Opinion as it is contrary to Matth. 10.10. 1 Cor. 9.11.—14. Gal. 6.6. and the practiſe of the Apoſtle himſelfe, 2 Co. 1.11. 9 Philip. 4.15.— 18. So it is generally contemned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            <p>It is beſt therefore to conſider, what thoſe ſay, which doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Miniſters a competency of meanes for their ſubſiſting. Some of them would have them enjoy the <hi>Tithes</hi> ſtill, being not only appointed for the Miniſtery of the Old Teſtament by God himſelf, but alſo if not commanded in, yet not contrary to the doctrine of the Goſpell in the New Teſtament. Others would have them depend and live upon the <hi>Gratuitie</hi> and Benevolency of the people, who would be willing to provide for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Miniſters, and that liberally. if they were left to their own will and diſcretion. The third ſort doth remit the care of providing for Miniſters to the <hi>Magiſtracie,</hi> who ſhould allow a certain yearly Penſion in money to the Miniſter; from the Publike, by this means to free them from all cares and troubles of the world?</p>
            <p>Now if you ask, whether any, or which of theſe three Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do ſhew us the moſt convenient and neareſt Goſpell-way for the Miniſters maintenance, I muſt conſeſſe, that it is to hard a matter for me to determine. All three Opinions, as they have their ſeverall conveniencies, ſo they ar not without their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall inconveniencies, which give me leave particularly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
            <div n="1" type="opinion">
               <head>The firſt Opinion.</head>
               <p>Firſt, it hath the plain Word of God for it under the Law, Num; 18.21. which being compared with Levit. 27.30. ſeem
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113834:3"/>to imply, that Tythes being abſolutely the Lords Portion, they were given to him by the Leviticall Miniſters, not as Leviticall, but as Miniſters, and ſo being derived, as it were, from them by entayle to Euangelical Miniſters, are now due to them, not as Evangelicall, but as the Miniſters of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt himſelf ſeemeth to approve of it in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Matth. 23.23. where he reproveth the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies not for paying the Tithes, but for doing no more.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Apoſtle ſeemeth in the Heb. 7.4. — 10. to build the ſtrongeſt foundation of his Doctrine, That the Prieſthood of Chriſt, being after the order of <hi>Melchinedecke,</hi> was more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then the Leviticall Prieſthood, upon this ground becauſe <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> took Tythes, even of <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of <hi>Levie</hi> in the loynes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe Poſterity ſhould receive Tithes. Now whether this ſuperexcellency of <hi>Mclchizedeck</hi> may be ſaid to be in his Antitype Jeſus Chriſt, if Chriſt neither taketh, nor hath right to take Tythes in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, is hard to decide.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, beſides the Apoſtles intimation of paying to the Miniſters ſomething of every good thing or bleſſing they enjoy, Gal. 6.6. Nay the Apoſtles inſerence, 1 Cor. 9.14. as if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel ſhould have their allowance by an expreſſe Ordinance of God <hi>It is ordained</hi> as the Leviticall Prieſts had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law: Now wee know of no other Ordinance of God concerning Miniſters maintenance, then that of Tythes.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the practice of Chriſtian Churches, afore, under, and after the reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, the conveniencie of ſuch a payment both in regard of proportion and eaſineſſe, the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeling any charge in it.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, the williugneſſe of moſt men to pay Tythes by reaſon of an old cuſtome, which is to them, <hi>altera natura.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fightly, and not to make them <hi>jure divine,</hi> the antient Lawes of the Kingdome, and the renewed Ordinances of Parliament do plead of the lawfulneſſe of them.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide it may be excepted againſt it:
<list>
                     <item>1 That the payment of Tythes being a meer Moſaical Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113834:4"/>was abrogated with the Levitical Prieſthood, Heb. 7.12.</item>
                     <item>2 That in the New Teſtament we finde not ſo much as a word of it.</item>
                     <item>3 That Chriſt and the Apoſtles neither took, nor comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor demanded them.</item>
                     <item>4 That other means are preſcribed in the Coſpel, for the maintenance of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as the ſecond Opinion will prove.</item>
                     <item>5 That in the firſt 200. years after Chriſt, there was no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it in Chriſtian Churches.</item>
                     <item>6 That paying of Tythes came not into the Church, till An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt began to ſtirre, and aiter many Superſtitions, were brought in by him.</item>
                     <item>7 That the State confirmed the payment of Tythes in the beginning of Reformation out of meer neceſſity, as they ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and connived to divers other Superſtitions, becauſe they durſt not offend the people too much, and knew not, how elſe to raiſe meanes for the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> which now we may do.</item>
                     <item>8 That the gathering of Tythes doth hinder <hi>Miniſters</hi> in their ſtudy and labours, and maketh them too worldly, and too proud, that many times they are liker Farmers or Graſiers, then Miniſters of the Goſpel.</item>
                     <item>9 That it is contrary to the practiſe of the beſt Reformed Churches.</item>
                     <item>10 That it is offenſive to many tender Conſciences, who would rather pay more then leſſe, if they were not forced to ſuch a kind of payment, and were left to their liberty: Nay, that many godly <hi>Miniſters</hi> groan under it, as a burden, and would fain be rid of it, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="opinion">
               <head>The ſecond Opinion.</head>
               <p>Firſt alleadgeth the Goſpel for it, where we have divers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, that the people did provide for their Miniſters freely, according to their own diſcretion, without having any certain ſet ſtipend, much leſſe Tythes paid to them, 2 Cor. 11.9. Phil. 4.18. Secondly, Chriſt himſelf received ſuch ſupplyes, Luke 8.3. Thirdly in all commands for the proviſion of Miniſters no certain kind or ſumme of dues is expreſt, but left to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113834:4"/>and ability of the people, 1 Cor. 9.11. — 14. Gal. 6.6 Now the Goſpel-way is the beſt way, and in ſuch duties wee ought to conforme rather to the Apoſtolical, then judaical pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe. Fourthly, it is a part of our Chriſtian liberty not to bee brought under the bondage of any man, but to do, freely, what we do, Gal. 5.1. Fifthly, the people will be more willing to doe rather above their ability than under, if they were left to their liberty, ſome in conſcience, ſome for their credit, ſome in love to their Miniſters, eſpecially if they may profit under them. Sixthly, <hi>Miniſter</hi> will find more comfort in ſuch free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will ofterings and contributions, then in all their forced tythes, and ſet ſtipends and wages. Seventhly, it will breed more love amongſt Miniſter and People. Eighthly, it will make Miniſters more painfull and carefull to approve themſelves to their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Ninthly it will teach Miniſters in all conditions to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and to know how to be abaſed, and how to abound, Phil. 4.11. Tenthly, it will free them from many cares and troubles of the world. And what ſhall we here deſire more then food and rayment? 1 Tim. 6.8.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide it may be ſaid, 1 That we have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample nor command in the whole New Teſtament, that the maintaining of Miniſters was ever left meerly to the diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people; but rather that in the primitive Churches, the people did and by reaſon of the Churches condition, were bound to pay more, then the tythes: in ſo much, that many ſould their whole eſtates, for the ſuſtenance of Miniſters and poore. Acts 4.34.37 Which now a dayes ſuch men would be loath to doe, that are ſo unwilling to pay the tenth part, not of their whole eſtate, but onely of their yeerly encreaſes to the Miniſters of the word. 2. That in the begining of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, afore Churches were ſettled and conſirmed under Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate, there could no certaine portion to be ſet out for the Miniſters maintenance, which yet was done as ſoon as under Chriſtian Magiſtrates the Churches were eſtabliſhed. 3 That the place of Scriptures alleageth ſpeake of the dutie in generall, that we ought to provide for Miniſters, not of the meanes or manner of performance, whether it ſhould be left
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113834:5"/>Arbytary to the peoples diſcretion, or be ordered by ſuperiors. Nay that thoſe places imploy rather a certaine ſet proportion, then an arbytrary contribution as it was ſhewn above. 4 That is no more a breach of our Chriſtian liberty, to pay a certain portion to the Miniſtery, then to pay certain ſet taxes, ſubſidies and cuſtomes to the Magiſtrates, which yet the Apoſtle teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth they have right unto, Rom. 13.7. 5 That the covetouſneſſe and worldlineſſe of men now a dayes is ſo great, that Miniſters ſhould have little enough to live upon with their Families, if they ſhould be forced to depend upon the gratuity and diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people, as in ſome places of late it did appear, to the great prejudice of Miniſters, and the greater ſhame of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. 6 That it would be very uncomfortable and diſgracefull to the Miniſters of God, to depend wholly upon, and to be behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto every particular member of his Congregation, be he never ſo mean or ſo bad for every bit of meat he puts into his mouth, though never ſo little; which were rather to live of the Goſpellors, then of the Goſpel, 1 Cor. 9.14. 7 That Miniſters may find much more comfort in the allowance of God, or the Magiſtrates, then in the ſelf-willing contribution of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. 8 That it would make Miniſters cowards in the Lords Work, and fearfull to offend the People, and rather prone to flatter and pleaſe them in their Doctrine, leaſt they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them their gratuity, or ſparingly contribute to them. 9 That it would rather increaſe their care to the world, not knowing what recompence they ſhal receive, then free and eaſe there of it. 10 That it would teach Miniſters to know, how to want, or to be abaſed but hardly how to abound. For their People would take an order with it, who thinks alwayes their Miniſters have too much. 11. That the ſame Apoſtle who will have us content with food and rayment, 1 Tim. 6.8. will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have us provide for our Families or elſe, that we deny the Faith, and are worſe then Inſidels, 1 Tim. 5.8. 12 That the chiefe ground of this opinion ſeemeth to be either envy or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, and that the abettors of it are either loath, that their Miniſters ſhould live comfortably with a ſufficient com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency, or unwilling to part with their dear Mammon for the Goſpels ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="opinion">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113834:5"/>
               <head>The third Opinion.</head>
               <p>As it is not contrary to Law and Goſpell, ſo it is grounded upon Reaſon and Equity; And 1 that as the Lord himſelf hath aſſigned in the Old Teſtament expreſly, and in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment implicitely, what kind and meaſure of reward his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhall have: So it is the duty of Magiſtrates, to ſee Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters duly recompenced for their pains, and not deprived of their portion. 2 That Godly Magiſtrates have at all times by vertue of their power, both under the Law and Goſpell taken care, that ſuch a ſet Portion was delivered to the Miniſters: Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> took care, Deut. 14.22. <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 Chron. 31.4.— 6. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 10.35, 37. And under the Goſpel, as ſoon as there was any Chriſtian Magiſtrate, from <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> they took care for the Miniſtery, and tythes were confirmed, though already paid afore even in <hi>Origens</hi> time, about 200. years after Chriſt. 3 Nay more, that Godly Magiſtrates gave order, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever dues were allowed to the Miniſtery, to be brought into certain treaſuries, and delivered to certain Commiſſioners, by whom they were afterwards proportionably diſtributed, ſo that Miniſters were freed from the trouble of gathering their tithes themſelves, as we read 2 Chron. 31. from v. 11. to v. 17. Neh. 12.44. and 13.12.13. 4 That God himſelf expreſly commandeth this courſe, Mal. 3.10, <hi>bring all the tithes into the Storehouſe.</hi> 5 That the Apoſtles in want of Chriſtian Magiſtrates perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſame duty, Act. 4.34, 37. Where all the contributions were laid to the Apoſtles feet, to be diſtributed proportionably as well to Miniſters, as the poor. 6 That this is a part of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributife Juſtice, to be executed by the Magiſtrates, to ſee, <hi>that theſe which are good, may have praiſe,</hi> Rom. 13.3. which is moſt neceſſary in the behalf of thoſe that labour for our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good, even the good of our ſoules; and conſequently, that ſuch as doe moſt good that way, or have moſt need of helpe, might receive moſt proportionably thoſe things that are fit for them, which cannot bee done, if every Miniſter taketh all the tythes of his own People, where many times unworthy ones have too much, and the worthieſt to little. 7 That by this means the great inequality of Miniſters meanes may be remedied, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113834:6"/>a better proportion ſet out and obſerved, leaſt ſome ſhould have all, and others nothing. 8 That Miniſters by this meanes will truly be freed from all worldly cares and troubles, &amp; have more liberty to wait on the Miniſtery of the word, not unlike the motion of the Apoſtles, Act. 6.2.4. 9 That the revenues of the Church may by this meanes be encreaſed, and the people by authority conſtrained to pay fully and truly that which oft they with-hold from the Miniſters, who dare not be ſo exact and ſtrict in their own right, leaſt they ſhould ſeeme to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting and covetous, as commonly they are ſlandered, when they will not let their people have all things at their own priſe. 10 That Miniſters being publike perſons, ſhould have their meanes from the Publike, without beeing beholding immediately to particular perſons, from whom they can can hardly get their dues without loſſe or ſtrife, or diſcontent. 11 That this is the juſteſt way of providing for Miniſters to receive their means proportionably to the time they have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if once a Quarter they ſhould be paid; Whereas now it ſeemeth to be moſt unjuſt, that if a Miniſter hath ſerved all the Year long, and ſhould dye afore the Harveſt, or afore the Corn be tythed, he loſeth that whole Years proſit, and his Succeſſour inneth one Years profit, afore he hath ſerved one moneth, and many times one Week. 12 That this is the practiſe of moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, and found to be the moſt convenient way for Miniſter and People. 13 That many godly Miniſters and Chriſtians in this Kingdome groan and long after it, &amp; would thank God for ir if it might be brought to paſſe. 14. That this would be a meanes to reconcile the two other Opinions, and make us all of one mind and judgment, as we ſhould be of one heart and affection.</p>
               <p>But it may be objected, 1. That it is out of the civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Sphere to meddle with Church-Affaires, and that wee muſt live by the Goſpel, not the <hi>Civill Law.</hi> 2. That it may be prejudicious to the Church, if <hi>Civill Magiſtrates</hi> ſhould have power to diſpoſe of Church-mens lands, that upon pretence of inevitable Neceſſities they may alienate all or part of them, and employ it in ſecular affaires, and bring the Miniſtery to want and poverty. 3 That there may be great partiality in the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Miniſters, and the aſſignation of ſet ſtipends, to certaine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113834:6"/>perſons and places, according as they have friends in high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 4 That under Officers and Collectors may be unfaithfull, and deceive the Miniſtery in the gatheeing of their meanes, or paying of them. 5 That great ſums of money muſt neceſſarily be taken from the Churches means, for the wages of ſuch col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors or treaſurers, which will impaire the Miniſters compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency. 6 That it will be as great, nay a greater trouble to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to get their penſion from thoſe collectors, or civil Officers then from the People. 7 That the people would bee more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to pay their dues to thoſe civill Officers, then to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters? ſome out of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> who are loath to pay tythes to Impropriators, becauſe they think they have no right to them; ſome out of <hi>Covetouſneſſe,</hi> becauſe then they will be more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly lookt unto, and will not have ſuch opportunity and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to deceive theſe collectors, as they did their Miniſters. 8 That Miniſters will be long detayned in their payment, if the collectors are negligent, and have not made their money of their commodities they receive, or if they are froward, and will not pay Miniſters at the times appointed. 9 That it is far more convenient for Miniſters, to have their ſeverall commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities in kind for the preſent uſe of their Families, then to have their penſion in money, and to buy every bit they eat, many times at a dear rate. 10 That Miniſters will be deprived of a great deale of recreation and refreſhment, when they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do in the field, and are lockt up as priſoners in their ſtudies, which will much annoy their health.</p>
               <p>Thus you have the conveniencies and inconveniencies of theſe ſeveral Opinions, repreſented to you, as near as may be, Your next queſtion, I know, now will be, which of theſe three Opinions I think the beſt and moſt convenient for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel. I confeſſe the matter is not only difficult, but odious, and which way ſoever I chuſe, I ſhall encurre the cenſure, if not the ill-will of ſome, which are of a contraſy opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. But this we muſt look for in all not only indiſterent, but the beſt things, eſpecialy in this age, where there are commonly <hi>tot ſententiae quot capita.</hi> And to tell you my mind freely, though
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113834:7"/>I will condemn none of the other Opinions, yet I doe now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to the third Opinion, which doth ſeeme to obſerue a <hi>Me, dium,</hi> &amp; goeth a middle way between the other two extreams, and may be a meanes to reconcile them both in time. I wil trouble you with no more reaſons, then were alleadged above. And concerning the objections againſt it, they ſeeme to me of no ſuch force and conſequence, as to make me ſtagger, or chang my mind.</p>
               <p>For 1. ſuppoſe the civil Magiſtrate have nothing to doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly with meere Church affaires, in points of faith and doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, but onely to be <hi>Cuſtosveritatis,</hi> and the defender of the faith eſtabliſhed, according to the word of God in the Churches of Chriſt: yet the care to provide for the Miniſters mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances ſafety belongs to them, as a duty of their civil power, as it was proved above. We do live by the Goſpell, that is not (as they ſeeme to inferre) by thoſe meanes, which the Church thinke good to aſſigne to the Miniſters for their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting: as popiſh prieſts preteud right to the tithes; by vertue of the Churches, or the Popes authoritie: but by thoſe means, which by publike authority of the civil Magiſtrates, or with their conſent by the liberality of the people is aſſigned to the Miniſtery for the preaching of the Goſpel. 2. The feare of having the Churches allowance diverted to ſecular uſes, is groundleſſe becauſe ſuch order muſt and will be taken by Act of Parliament that the Receivers or Treaſurer of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call revenues, which are to be eſtabliſhed for the payment of Miniſters, may be ſecured from all ſuch ſecular encroachments and invaſions, and obliged by death to employ thoſe Church revenues onely for the uſe appointed, notwithſtanding all commands or orders from any power whatſoever. And this we know duely practiſed and obſerved in divers Reformed Churches and Dominions beyond the ſea, wherein the greateſt neceſſities of the Sate, the Church revenues were not touched unleſſe the Sate did perhaps borrow a part of the overplus of Church revenues, that was left over and above the full pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Miniſters, which yet was faithfully repayed with the firſt commodity. And If we feare, the Parliament might
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113834:7"/>repeale ſuch Lawes and Acts, or for the preſent connive to the breach of them, then we may as well feare, the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might repeale the Act for paying of Tithes, and in time of extremity enjoy all or part of them to publike uſes: as the Popenow and then diſpenſeth with Kings and Princes, to ſeaſe upon the tythes, revenues, nay the very moveables of the Church for ſecular uſe. But we have no cauſe to feare ſuch violence in the high Court of Parliament, which is more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the preſervation of Gods Miniſters, and hath many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other wayes to provide for ſufficiencie of meanes in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt extremity, as we have experience of in theſe preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions. 3. Neither have we any juſt cauſe to feare partiality in the aſignation of ſtipends and meanes, which ſhall be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated according to the quality of perſons and places, by ſuch as are faithfull in the land, and entrnſted with greater matters: eſpecially becauſe all Miniſters ſhall have a ſufficient compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie, though ſome more then others, in regard of their deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſſe and employments. And is there a greater parliallity now, when my Lord, or Sir, ſuch a one doth beſtow a living of 2 3, hunnred a yeare, upon his younger brother, or kinſinan, or one that marryed his poore kinſwoman, or his Ladies cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bermaid, though that Miniſter be never ſo ignorant or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and wany times doth agree for a ſum of money beſides to be paid him out of the yeerly meanes: when a well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man can hardly get a living to live upon; where is like to be more partiality; 4. Under officers and collectors muſt be warily choſen and often called to account, that they may not have much time to deceive &amp; if found guilty ſeverly puniſhed <hi>In terrorem,</hi> that others may take warning &amp; be faithful. Neither can they deceive much, becauſe it is geuerally known, what the livings are worth, and what can be made of them: and the people will be carefull enough to watch and betray them, if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, becauſe generally they hate ſuch kind of men. And Miniſters themſelves muſt truſt the people many times with their tithes, and take what they give, or their Bailiffe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who are often more unfaithfull, then ſuch men can be. 5. the pay or wages of ſuch collectors will not mount to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113834:8"/>very much, and ſcarce be felt as ſhall be ſhewen in due time: ſure not ſo much by far, as Miniſters charges do amount unto for the inning of their tithes, and manuring their glebe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by this meanes they ſhall be freed from all, and have their meanes comming in without charge or trouble. 6. Miniſters ſhall not be troubled to beg their ſtipend from thoſe collectors, but ſhall have it ſent or delivered them by the Committee for Eccleſiaſticall revenues, reſiding in every County, without faile, at the times appointed. of which order I will informe you hereafter God willing. And this we know very orderly and carefully executed and performed in divers Countries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, though now by reaſon of the newneſſe &amp; ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it ſeeme difficult, if not impoſſible to us in theſe parts. 7 It is uncertain, whether the people will pay their dues more unwillingly to the Collectors, then to the Miniſters, it may bee ſome will, though ſome will not. But whether willing or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to pay their dues to the civil Magiſtrates, becauſe they know there is no reſiſting againſt them, they muſt doe it at the laſt whether they will or not. But whether willing or not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it matters not, if it be enacted in Parliament, a neceſſity is llaid upon them to do it. 8 Neither will Miniſters be longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the payment of their ſtipends, then now they are, where they muſt ſtay ſometimes ſix moneths, ſometimes lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, from Harveſt to Eaſter, from one Harveſt to another, afore they can have their competency to any purpoſe: Whereas then they ſhall have their portion paid them every Quarter day and truly. 9 There is no commodity without a diſcommodity, yet both being compared together in this caſe, the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a ſet ſtipend duly paid, and coming in without charge or trouble are far greater then the incommodities. Suppoſe Miniſters cannot have every thing in kind, as Lambes, Wool, Pigs, Egges, Fruits, and ſuch kind of ſmall tythes, yet it will be no great loſſe to them. For Miniſters did for the moſt part ſell their Lambes and Wool, and made no uſe of it in kind: and as for the reſt of ſmall tythes, Pigs, Fruits, Egges, and ſuch trifles may eaſily be had every where at a ſmall prize, the loſſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113834:8"/>in kind cannot countervalue the great commodity, which they ſhal enjoy by a certain ſtipend. Notwithſtanding, they ſhal have ſome wheat, corn, hay, wood, &amp; the like proviſion in kind, if it pleaſe them to ſerve their neceſſities. 10 As it is fit, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould have ſome recreations to refreſh their ſpirits after meditations and labours; ſo it is very unfit, Miniſters ſhould make the world their recreation, as if no relaxation could be had for them, but to plough and to ſow, to buy and to ſell, and to play the Farmers and Grafiers. There are other more fitter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations for the body in honeſt exerciſes, gardenings, &amp;c. which ſhall be allowed them for their refreſhment.</p>
               <p>And thus I have briefly anſwered, and as I hope, ſatisfactorily to ſuch objections, as are or may be made againſt the third Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. I leave all to your charitable conſtruction and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, having only upon your importunity opened to you my private opinion, which I truſt will in no wayes be prejudicious, neither to the deſire of the Miniſtery, nor the determination of the State. By the next, if poſſible, I will endeavovr to open ſome way, how Miniſters meanes may be gathered without their trouble, equally diſtributed, and the Church Revenues augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. In the mean while I commend you to the Lord, and reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
